Ladies and gentlemen...
ਇਸਤਰੀ ਅਤ ਲਕ ...
Well, gentlemen certainly. This is no place for a lady.
ਠੀਕ ਹ, ਲਕ ਰਰ. ਇਹ ਇੱਕ ਔਰਤ ਲਈ ਕਈ ਜਾ ਹ.
MEN SNIGGER.
ਲਕ ਹੱਸਦ.
It gives me great pleasure, and no small amount of relief,
ਮਨ ਇਹ ਬਹਤ ਖੀ ਰਾਹਤ ਦੀ ਕਈ ਛਟੀ ਰਕਮ ਦਿਦਾ ਹ, ਅਤ,
to declare this, the first ever flushing public lavatory, open.
ਇਸ ਦਾ ਐਲਾਨ ਕਰਨ ਲਈ, ਪਹਿਲੀ ਅਤਟਾੱਇਲਟ ਜਨਤਕ ਪਖਾਨ ', ਓਪਨ.
APPLAUSE.
ਸਸਾ.
WHISTLING.
ਸੀਟੀ.
Might want to leave it five minutes.
ਇਸ ਨ ਪਜ ਮਿਟ ਛੱਡਣ ਲਈ ਚਾਹਦ ਹ ਸਕਦਾ ਹ.
HE GASPS. Oh, my goodness!
ਉਸ ਨ ਸਾਹ ਖਿੱਚਦਾ. ਉਹ ਮਰ ਰੱਬਾ!
A year previously, in 1851,
ਇਕ ਸਾਲ ਪਿਛਲੀ, 1851 ਵਿੱਚ,
temporary toilets were exhibited at the Great Exhibition in London's Hyde Park
ਆਰੀ ਪਖਾਨ ਲਡਨ ਦ ਹਾਈਡ ਪਾਰਕ ਵਿਚ ਮਹਾਨ ਪਰਦਰਨੀ 'ਤ ਪਰਦਰਿਤ ਕੀਤਾ ਗਿਆ ਸੀ
and visitors were charged a penny to use them.
ਅਤ ਸਲਾਨੀ ਨ ਇੱਕ ਸਿੱਕਾ ਨ ਵਰਤਣ ਲਈ ਚਾਰਜ ਕੀਤਾ ਗਿਆ ਸੀ.
That is thought to be the origin of the phrase "to spend a penny".
ਇਹ ਬਦ ਦਾ ਮਲ "ਇੱਕ ਸਿੱਕਾ ਖਰਚ ਕਰਨ 'ਹਣ ਲਈ ਸਚਿਆ ਹ.
And this is the origin of the Nobel Peace Prize.
ਅਤ ਇਹ ਨਬਲ ਅਮਨ ਪਰਸਕਾਰ ਦਾ ਮਲ ਹ.
Hm, interesting.
ਅੱਛਾ. ਦਿਲਚਸਪ.
But that's not what's supposed to happen.
ਪਰ, ਜ ਕਿ ਕੀ ਹ ਕਰਨ ਲਈ ਚਾਹੀਦਾ ਹ, ਨਾ ਹ.
Darling, I don't want to worry you or anything,
ਡਾਰਲਿਗ, ਮਨ ਨਾ ਤਹਾਨ ਜ ਕਝ ਵੀ ਚਿਤਾ ਕਰਨ ਦੀ ਚਾਹਦ,
- but I think you might be dead. - Hm?
- ਪਰ ਮਨ ਲੱਗਦਾ ਹ ਕਿ ਤਹਾਨ ਮਰਦਾ ਹ ਸਕਦਾ ਹ. - ਜੀ?
I don't think so, darling.
ਮਨ ਇਸ ਲਈ ਨਾ ਸਚ, ਤਾਈ.
This newspaper seems to think you are, and it's always been very reliable in the past.
ਇਹ ਅਖਬਾਰ ਸਚਣ ਲਈ ਤਹਾਨ ਹਨ ਲੱਗਦਾ ਹ, ਅਤ ਇਸ ਨ ਹਮਾ ਪਿਛਲ ਵਿੱਚ ਬਹਤ ਹੀ ਭਰਸਯਗ ਗਿਆ ਹ.
“Doctor Alfred Nobel, the Swedish chemist and inventor of dynamite,
"ਡਾਕਟਰ Alfred ਨਬਲ, ਸਵੀਡਨੀ ਕਮਿਸਟ ਅਤ ਡਾਇਨਾਮਾਈਟ ਦੀ ਖਜ,
“died yesterday in the French resort of Cannes.”
"ਕਨਸ ਦ ਹ French ਪਾਰਕ ਵਿੱਚ ਕੱਲਹ ਮਤ ਹ ਗਈ."
Let me see that.
ਮਨ ਹ, ਜ ਕਿ ਦਖੀਏ.
Good grief, it does say I'm dead.
ਚਗਾ ਦੱਖ ਹ, ਇਸ ਨ ਮਨ ਮਰ ਰਿਹਾ ਕਹਿਦੀ ਹ.
Look what they're calling me, “the merchant of death”.
ਵਖ ਕਿ ਕੀ ਉਹ ਮਰ 'ਮਤ ਦ ਵਪਾਰੀ' ਨ ਕਾਲ ਕਰ ਰਹ ਹ,.
It says here, “Dr Alfred Nobel became rich
ਇਥ ਇਹ ਆਖਦਾ ਹ, "ਡਾ Alfred ਨਬਲ ਅਮੀਰ ਬਣ ਗਏ
“by finding ways to kill more people even faster than ever before.”
"ਹਰ ਲਕ ਨ ਮਾਰਨ ਲਈ ਤਰੀਕ ਵੀ ਤੀ ਨਾਲ ਅੱਗ ਕਦ ਵੱਧ ਲੱਭਣ ਕ."
You'd think that just because I'd invented dynamite,
ਤਹਾਨ ਲੱਗਦਾ ਹ, ਜ ਕਿ ਦੀ ਕਾਢ ਡਾਇਨਾਮਾਈਟ ਹਣ ਹੀ, ਕਿਉਕਿ ਮਨ ਆਏਗਾ ਆਏਗਾ
I am personally responsible for the death of thousands of people!
ਮਨ ਲਕ ਦ ਹਾਰ ਦੀ ਮਤ ਲਈ ਨਿੱਜੀ ਤਰ 'ਤ ਿਮਵਾਰ ਹ!
I mean honestly, have you ever heard such nonsense? CLOCK TICKS.
ਮਨ ਇਮਾਨਦਾਰੀ, ਜਕਰ ਤਹਾਨ ਕਦ ਵੀ ਅਜਿਹ ਬਕਵਾਸ ਸਣਿਆ ਹ ਮਤਲਬ ਹ? ਘੜੀ ਟਿਕ.
I said, have you ever heard such rubbish?
ਮਨ ਕਿਹਾ, 'ਤਹਾਨ ਕਦ ਵੀ ਅਜਿਹ ਕੜ ਸਣਿਆ ਹ?
Sophie, if you have something to say...
ਸੀ, ਜਕਰ ਤਹਾਨ ਕਝ ਕਹਿਣ ਲਈ ਹ ...
Well, you did invent what is, at this point in time,
ਨਾਲ ਨਾਲ, ਤਹਾਨ ਕਾਢ ਸੀ ਕੀ ਵਾਰ ਵਿਚ ਇਸ ਮਕ 'ਤ ਹ,
the most powerful explosive on earth.
ਧਰਤੀ 'ਤ ਸਭ ਕਤੀਾਲੀ ਵਿਸਫਟਕ.
- And it has gone on to kill thousands of people. - What's your point?
- ਅਤ ਇਸ 'ਤ ਚਲਾ ਗਿਆ ਹ ਲਕ ਦ ਹਾਰ ਨ ਮਾਰਨ ਲਈ. - ਆਪਣ ਬਿਦ ਕੀ ਹ?
All I'm saying is, you have to accept when people hear the word "Nobel",
ਸਾਰ ਮਨ ਹੀ ਕਹਿ ਰਿਹਾ ਹ, ਤਹਾਨ ਸਵੀਕਾਰ ਕਰਨ ਲਈ, ਜਦ ਲਕ ਬਚਨ ਨ ਸਣਦ "ਨਬਲ" ਹ,
they're always going to think of dynamite.
ਉਹ ਹਮਾ ਡਾਇਨਾਮਾਈਟ ਦੀ ਸਚਦ ਕਰਨ ਲਈ ਜਾ ਰਹ ਹ.
I knew I should've called it Nobel's Safety Powder.
ਮਨ ਇਸ ਨ ਨਬਲ ਦੀ ਸਰੱਖਿਆ ਪਾਉਡਰ ਕਹਿਦ ਕੀਤਾ ਹ ਚਾਹੀਦਾ ਹ ਸੀ.
Do you really think that when I actually do go that this is how I'll be remembered?
ਤਹਾਨ ਅਸਲ ਵਿੱਚ ਸਚਦ ਹ ਕਿ ਜਾਣ ਹ, ਜ ਕਿ ਇਸ ਨ ਮਨ ਯਾਦ ਕੀਤਾ ਲੱਗਗਾ ਹ, ਜਦ ਮਨ ਅਸਲ ਵਿੱਚ ਕਰਦ ਹਨ?
Oh, sweetheart, of course it is, my furry-cheeked little death merchant.
ਓ, ਸਵੀਟਹਾਰਟ, ਦ ਕਰਸ ਇਸ ਨ ਹ, ਮਰ furry-cheeked ਜਿਹਾ ਮਤ ਦਾ ਵਪਾਰੀ.
Well, not if I can help it!
ਠੀਕ ਹ, ਜ ਨਾ ਮਨ ਇਸ ਨ ਮਦਦ ਕਰ ਸਕਦਾ ਹ!
I shall reinvent my own image.
ਮਨ ਮਰ ਆਪਣ ਹੀ ਚਿੱਤਰ ਨ ਰਨਵਿਟ ਚਾਹੀਦਾ ਹ.
- What? - I shall use my massive fortune to establish a special prize.
- ਕੀ? - ਮਨ ਮਰ ਵੱਡ ਕਿਸਮਤ ਨ ਇੱਕ ਵਿ ਇਨਾਮ ਨ ਸਥਾਪਤ ਕਰਨ ਲਈ ਇਸਤਮਾਲ ਕਰਗਾ.
One that rewards positive human endeavours in the pursuit of peace
ਇਕ ਹ, ਜ ਕਿ ਅਮਨ ਦਾ ਪਿੱਛਾ ਸਕਾਰਾਤਮਕ ਮਨੱਖੀ ਕਿ ਨ ਇਨਾਮ
so that when I do die, I won't just be linked to explosives!
ਜ ਕਿ ਇਸ ਲਈ, ਜਦ ਮਨ ਮਰਦ ਹਨ, ਮਨ ਹਣ ਹੀ ਵਿਸਫਟਕ ਨਾਲ ਜੜਿਆ ਨਾ ਕੀਤਾ ਜਾਵਗਾ!
And I, Alfred Nobel, will call this special peace prize...
ਅਤ ਮਨ, Alfred ਨਬਲ, ਇਸ ਵਿ ਅਮਨ ਪਰਸਕਾਰ ਨ ਕਾਲ ਕਰ ਜਾਵਗਾ ...
Prize-A-Mite!
Prize-A-Mite!
Darling, why don't you call it the Nobel Peace Prize?
ਡਾਰਲਿਗ, ਤ ਇਸ ਨ ਨਬਲ ਅਮਨ ਪਰਸਕਾਰ ਨ ਕਾਲ ਨਾ ਕਰ?
HE CHUCKLES.
ਉਹ ਹੱਸਦਾ ਹ.
I love you, darling, but you have absolutely no idea when it comes to marketing.
ਮਨ ਤਹਾਡ ਨਾਲ ਪਿਆਰ, ਮਿੱਠੜੀ, ਪਰ ਤਹਾਨ ਬਿਲਕਲ ਕਈ ਵੀ ਵਿਚਾਰ ਹ, ਜਦ ਇਸ ਨ ਮਾਰਕੀਟਿਗ ਕਰਨ ਲਈ ਆਇਆ ਹ.
- A-hem! Tea! - Certainly.
- ਇੱਕ-ਪੱਲਾ! ਚਾਹ! - ਬਿਲਕਲ.